On the 30th of May, 1832,
في ٣٠ من ماي ١٨٣٢
a gunshot was heard
طلقة مسدس سمعت
ringing out across the 13th arrondissement in Paris.
رنت صوتها عبر أنحاء المقاطعة ١٣ في باريس
(Gunshot)
(طلقة مسدس)
A peasant, who was walking to market that morning,
في ذالك الصباح، و بينما كان أحد الرعاة في طريقه للتسوق
ran towards where the gunshot had come from,
هرع مسرعا نحو مصدرالطلقة
and found a young man writhing in agony on the floor,
ليجد شابا صريعا فوق الثراب
clearly shot by a dueling wound.
كان واضحا أنه قد جرح خلال مجابهة
The young man's name was Evariste Galois.
هذا الشاب كان يسمى، أوڨاريست ڴالوا
He was a well-known revolutionary in Paris at the time.
كان ثوريا معروفا أنذاك في باريس
Galois was taken to the local hospital
حمل ڴالوا إلى الطبيب المحلي
where he died the next day in the arms of his brother.
حيث توفي بين يدي أخيه في اليوم التالي
And the last words he said to his brother were,
آخر كلماته لأخيه،
"Don't cry for me, Alfred.
"لا تبكي علي يا ألفريد.
I need all the courage I can muster
فإني محتاج لجمع كل ما أقدر عليه من الشجاعة
to die at the age of 20."
لأتوفي في عمر العشرين."
It wasn't, in fact, revolutionary politics
في حقيقة الأمر، لم تكن الثورية السياسية
for which Galois was famous.
ما كان معروفا به ڴالوا.
But a few years earlier, while still at school,
لكن قبل عدة سنوات، و حينما كان بالمدرسة،
he'd actually cracked one of the big mathematical
قام بحل واحد من أكبر
problems at the time.
المسائل الرياضية حينها.
And he wrote to the academicians in Paris,
لقد وجه عمله إلى الأكاديميين في باريس،
trying to explain his theory.
في محاولة لتفسير نظريته.
But the academicians couldn't understand anything that he wrote.
لكن الأكادميين لم يتمكنوا من فهم أي شيء مما كتب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is how he wrote most of his mathematics.
هكذا، كيف كان يكتب معظم رياضياته.
So, the night before that duel, he realized
خلال الليلة قبيل المجابهة، أدرك
this possibly is his last chance
أن هذه ربما آخر فرصة له
to try and explain his great breakthrough.
ليحاول تفسير تقدمه العظيم.
So he stayed up the whole night, writing away,
فأمضى طوال الليل يكتب،
trying to explain his ideas.
في محاولة لتفسير أفكاره.
And as the dawn came up and he went to meet his destiny,
و حينما أقبل الفجر، توجه لملاقاة قدره،
he left this pile of papers on the table for the next generation.
ترك للأجيال القادمة، كومة من الأوراق فوق الطاولة
Maybe the fact that he stayed up all night doing mathematics
من الممكن أن إمضاءه تلك الليلة في كتابة الرياضيات
was the fact that he was such a bad shot that morning and got killed.
هو ما قد تسبب في قتله ذالك الصباح.
But contained inside those documents
لكن ما كانت تحتوي عليه تلك الأوراق
was a new language, a language to understand
كان لغة جديدة، لغة لفهم
one of the most fundamental concepts
واحد من المفاهيم الأساسية
of science -- namely symmetry.
في الميدان العلمي - ما يسمى "التماثل"
Now, symmetry is almost nature's language.
إن التماثل هو لغة الطبيعة
It helps us to understand so many
إنه يساعدنا على فهم
different bits of the scientific world.
أجزاء مختلفة من الميدان العلمي.
For example, molecular structure.
من بين الأمثلة نجد، بنية الجزيئة.
What crystals are possible,
أي بنية بلورية يمكن الحصول عليها
we can understand through the mathematics of symmetry.
يمكن أن تفهم عبر رياضيات التماثل.
In microbiology you really don't want to get a symmetrical object,
في علم الأحياء الدقيقة لا نريد الحصول على كائنات متماثلة.
because they are generally rather nasty.
لأنها في معظم الوقت مخلوقات مزعجة.
The swine flu virus, at the moment, is a symmetrical object.
حاليا، أنفلولزا الخنازير لكائن متماثل.
And it uses the efficiency of symmetry
وهو يستغل كفائة التماثل
to be able to propagate itself so well.
ليتمكن من التكاثر بفعالية.
But on a larger scale of biology, actually symmetry is very important,
لكننا نجد أن التماثل جد مهم، على مستوى المشهد البيولوجي العام،
because it actually communicates genetic information.
لأنه يكشف عن المعلومات الجينية.
I've taken two pictures here and I've made them artificially symmetrical.
لقد أخذت صورتان و جعلتهما متماثلتان بطريقة إصطناعية.
And if I ask you which of these you find more beautiful,
و إذا سألتكم أي صورة تجدون أجمل،
you're probably drawn to the lower two.
ستختارون و بالتأكيد الصورتان بالأسفل.
Because it is hard to make symmetry.
لأنه من الصعب الحصول على التماثل.
And if you can make yourself symmetrical, you're sending out a sign
و عندما تستطيع الحصول على بنية متماثلة، فإنك ترسل إشارة
that you've got good genes, you've got a good upbringing
على أنك تحمل جينات متناسقة، و أنك ذو تنشئة حسنة
and therefore you'll make a good mate.
وتشكل بالتالي شريكا جيدا.
So symmetry is a language which can help to communicate
فبذالك يشكل التماثل لغة تساعد على إيصال
genetic information.
المعلومات الجينية.
Symmetry can also help us to explain
يساعدنا التماثل أيضا على تفسير
what's happening in the Large Hadron Collider in CERN.
ما يحدث ب " مصادم الهادرون الكبير" في لابوراتوار "سيرن"
Or what's not happening in the Large Hadron Collider in CERN.
أو ما لا يحدث هنالك.
To be able to make predictions about the fundamental particles
لكي نتمكن من توقع مميزات الجسيمات الأولية الأساسية
we might see there,
التي يمكن أن نشاهد هناك،
it seems that they are all facets of some strange symmetrical shape
يتبين أنها أوجه شكل هندسي متماثل و غريب
in a higher dimensional space.
يوجد داخل فضاء متعدد الأبعاد.
And I think Galileo summed up, very nicely,
و إني أعتقد أن كاليليو قد لخص، و بأسلوب رائع،
the power of mathematics
قوة الرياضيات،
to understand the scientific world around us.
التي تمكننا من فهم العالم حولنا.
He wrote, "The universe cannot be read
فيقول، "لن نستطيع قراءة الكون
until we have learnt the language
حتى أن نتعلم اللغة
and become familiar with the characters in which it is written.
و نتعود على الحروف التي تكتب بها.
It is written in mathematical language,
إنه مكتوب بلغة رياضية.
and the letters are triangles, circles and other geometric figures,
و المثلث، الدائرة، و الأشكال الهندسية الأخرى هي حروفها
without which means it is humanly impossible
و التي دونها لا يمكن للإنسان
to comprehend a single word."
أن يفهم أي كلمة."
But it's not just scientists who are interested in symmetry.
لكن ليس العلماء وحدهم الذين يهتمون بالتماثل.
Artists too love to play around with symmetry.
إن الفنانين أيضا يحبون اللعب بالتماثل.
They also have a slightly more ambiguous relationship with it.
هم كذلك لهم صلة غريبة به.
Here is Thomas Mann talking about symmetry in "The Magic Mountain."
هكذا نجد طوماس مان يتكلم على التماثل في "الجبل السحري"
He has a character describing the snowflake,
حيث تصف أحد شخصياته نذفة الثلج.
and he says he "shuddered at its perfect precision,
و يقول أنه " قد ارتعش من دقته الكاملة،
found it deathly, the very marrow of death."
وجد أنها تحمل ذوق الموت، نخاع الموت."
But what artists like to do is to set up expectations
و لكن الفنانين يحبون وضع توقعات
of symmetry and then break them.
تماثلية ثم القيام بكسرها.
And a beautiful example of this
من بين أجمل الأمثلة على هذا
I found, actually, when I visited a colleague of mine
وجدتها حينما زرت أحد أصدقائي
in Japan, Professor Kurokawa.
في اليابان، بروفسور كوروكاوا.
And he took me up to the temples in Nikko.
اخذني معبد في نيكو.
And just after this photo was taken we walked up the stairs.
بعدما أخذنا هذه الصورة، صعدنا الأدرج.
And the gateway you see behind
تحمل تملك البوابة التي ترونها في الخلفية
has eight columns, with beautiful symmetrical designs on them.
ثمانية أعمدة، ذات تصميم متماثل و جميل.
Seven of them are exactly the same,
يتطابق سبع منهم تماما
and the eighth one is turned upside down.
لكن الثامن مقلوب رأسا على عقب.
And I said to Professor Kurokawa,
فقلت للبروفيسور كوروكاوا،
"Wow, the architects must have really been kicking themselves
"واو، لا بد أن المهندسين أحرجوا
when they realized that they'd made a mistake and put this one upside down."
لما تبين لهم خطأهم."
And he said, "No, no, no. It was a very deliberate act."
فأجاب، "لا لا لا. إنه عمل متعمد"
And he referred me to this lovely quote from the Japanese
و ذكر لي هذه القولة اليابينية الجميلة
"Essays in Idleness" from the 14th century,
مقتطفة من "مقالات في الفراغ" من القرن ١٤.
in which the essayist wrote, "In everything,
حيث يقول الكاتب، "في كل شيء،
uniformity is undesirable.
لا نفضل النظام.
Leaving something incomplete makes it interesting,
جعل شيء ما غير كامل، يزيده أهمية.
and gives one the feeling that there is room for growth."
و يعطينا إحساسا بأنه هنالك مجال للتحسين."
Even when building the Imperial Palace,
حتى خلال بناء القصر الإمبراطوري،
they always leave one place unfinished.
فإنهم يدعون قطعة غير كاملة.
But if I had to choose one building in the world
إذا خيرت أي مبنى في العالم
to be cast out on a desert island, to live the rest of my life,
لأقضي به الباقي من حياتي، وسط جزيرة فارغة،
being an addict of symmetry, I would probably choose the Alhambra in Granada.
و بكوني مولع بالتماثل، سأختار قصر الحمراء بغرناطة.
This is a palace celebrating symmetry.
يشكل هذا القصر نشيدا للتماثل.
Recently I took my family --
أخذت مؤخرا عائلتي -
we do these rather kind of nerdy mathematical trips, which my family love.
نقوم بهذا النوع من الرحلات الرياضية، و التي تحبها عائلتي.
This is my son Tamer. You can see
هذا إبني تامر. كما ترون
he's really enjoying our mathematical trip to the Alhambra.
يستمتع برحلتنا الرياضية في قصر الحمراء.
But I wanted to try and enrich him.
إني أريد أن أغني معرفته.
I think one of the problems about school mathematics
إني أعتقد أن المشكل في تعليم الرياضيات
is it doesn't look at how mathematics is embedded
هو أنه لا يرتكز حول علاقة
in the world we live in.
الرياضيات بالعالم الذي نعيش فيه.
So, I wanted to open his eyes up to
و هكذا أردت أن أفتح عينيه على
how much symmetry is running through the Alhambra.
وجود التماثل عبر أنحاء قصر الحمراء.
You see it already. Immediately you go in,
أول شيء نراه
the reflective symmetry in the water.
هو الإنعكاس التماثلي في الماء.
But it's on the walls where all the exciting things are happening.
لكن الأكثر تشويقا هو ما يوجد على الجدران.
The Moorish artists were denied the possibility
قد منع على الفنانين البربر
to draw things with souls.
من تمثيل كائنات حية.
So they explored a more geometric art.
و بذالك قاموا باكتشاف الفن الهندسي.
And so what is symmetry?
فما هو التماثل؟
The Alhambra somehow asks all of these questions.
يطرح قصر الحمراء بطريقة ما كل هذه الأسئلة.
What is symmetry? When [there] are two of these walls,
ما هو التماثل؟ عندما لدينا جدارين،
do they have the same symmetries?
هل لهما نفس الأشكال المتماثلة؟
Can we say whether they discovered
هل يمكننا أن نأكد يأنهم قد اكتشفوا
all of the symmetries in the Alhambra?
كل طرق التماثل بقصر الحمراء؟
And it was Galois who produced a language
ڴالوا هو الذي قام باكتشاف اللغة
to be able to answer some of these questions.
التي تمكننا من الإجابة على البعض من هذه الأسئلة.
For Galois, symmetry -- unlike for Thomas Mann,
إن التماثل بالنسبة لڴالوا - على عكس طوماس مان،
which was something still and deathly --
الذي يراه ساكنا و مميتا --
for Galois, symmetry was all about motion.
إن التماثل بالنسبة لڴالوا يتجسد في الحركة.
What can you do to a symmetrical object,
ماذا يمكن أن نفعل بكائن متماثل،
move it in some way, so it looks the same
تحريكه بطريقة ما، حتى يبدو على نفس الهيئة
as before you moved it?
التي كان عليها قبل تحريكه؟
I like to describe it as the magic trick moves.
أحب وصف ذالك بخدعة الحركة.
What can you do to something? You close your eyes.
ماذا يمكن أن تفعل لشيء ما؟ أغمض عينيك.
I do something, put it back down again.
أحركه، و أرجعه إلى مكانه.
It looks like it did before it started.
فيبدو كما في حالته البدائية.
So, for example, the walls in the Alhambra --
فعلى سبيل المثال، جدران قصر الحمراء،
I can take all of these tiles, and fix them at the yellow place,
يمكن أن آخذ كل هاته القطع، و وضعهم فوق المنطقة الصفراء،
rotate them by 90 degrees,
أديرهم بزاوية ٩٠ درجة،
put them all back down again and they fit perfectly down there.
و عندما أرجعهم إلى المكان الأولي، يتطابقون تماما.
And if you open your eyes again, you wouldn't know that they'd moved.
و عندما تفتح عينيك لن تستطيع القول أن القطع قد تحركت.
But it's the motion that really characterizes the symmetry
لكن الحركة هي التي تميز التماثل
inside the Alhambra.
بداخل قصر الحمراء.
But it's also about producing a language to describe this.
لكن الأمر يهم أيضا إنتاج لغة لوصف كل هذا.
And the power of mathematics is often
غالبا ما نجد أن قوة الرياضيات
to change one thing into another, to change geometry into language.
تتمثل في تغيير شيء ما إلى آخر، تغيير هندسة ما إلى لغة.
So I'm going to take you through, perhaps push you a little bit mathematically --
و بهذا سأقوم بقيادتكم، ربما أضغط قليلا على معلوماتكم الرياضية -
so brace yourselves --
فتمسكوا جيدا -
push you a little bit to understand how this language works,
سأدفعكم قليلا لفهم هذه اللغة،
which enables us to capture what is symmetry.
التي تمكننا من فهم التماثل.
So, let's take these two symmetrical objects here.
فلنأخذ على سبيل المثال هذين الشكلين المتماثلين.
Let's take the twisted six-pointed starfish.
لنأخذ مثال نجم البحر السداسي الملتوي.
What can I do to the starfish which makes it look the same?
ماذا يمكنني أن أفعل بنجم البحر فيبدو على نفس الهيئة؟
Well, there I rotated it by a sixth of a turn,
أديره بسدس دورة كاملة،
and still it looks like it did before I started.
فيأخذ هيئته البدائية.
I could rotate it by a third of a turn,
يمكنني أن أديره بثلث دورة،
or a half a turn,
أو نصف دورة،
or put it back down on its image, or two thirds of a turn.
أو أرجعه إلى مكانه، أو أديره ثلثي دورة.
And a fifth symmetry, I can rotate it by five sixths of a turn.
و في تماثل خامس، يمكن أن أديره بخمس سدس من الدورة.
And those are things that I can do to the symmetrical object
كل هذا يشكل ما يمكن أن أفعل بشكل متماثل
that make it look like it did before I started.
حتى أجعله على نفس الهيئة قبل أن أبدأ بتحريكه.
Now, for Galois, there was actually a sixth symmetry.
في حقيقة الأمر بالنسبة لڴالوا، هنالك تماثل سادس.
Can anybody think what else I could do to this
هل يمكن لأحد ما أن يجد حركة أخرى
which would leave it like I did before I started?
بجعل الشكل على حالته الأولية؟
I can't flip it because I've put a little twist on it, haven't I?
لا يمكنني قلبه لأني حرفته قليلا، ألم أفعل؟
It's got no reflective symmetry.
إنه لا يمتلك أي تماثل محوري.
But what I could do is just leave it where it is,
فقط، يمكن أن أتركه في مكانه،
pick it up, and put it down again.
أرفعه من مكانه، ثم أضعه.
And for Galois this was like the zeroth symmetry.
و كان هذا التماثل رقم صفر بالنسبة لڴالوا.
Actually, the invention of the number zero
في حقيقة الأمر كان إختراع الصفر
was a very modern concept, seventh century A.D., by the Indians.
مفهوما حديثا، القرن السابع ق.م، من قبل الهنود.
It seems mad to talk about nothing.
قد يبدوا التكلم عن العدم جنونا.
And this is the same idea. This is a symmetrical --
نجد نفس الفكرة هنا. هذا تماثل --
so everything has symmetry, where you just leave it where it is.
و بذالك كل شيء له تماثل، حينما تتركه في مكانه.
So, this object has six symmetries.
و بالتالي، يتوفر هذا الشكل على ستة تماثلات.
And what about the triangle?
فماذا بالنسبة للمثلث؟
Well, I can rotate by a third of a turn clockwise
يمكنني أن أديره بثلث دورة باتجاه عقارب الساعة
or a third of a turn anticlockwise.
أو عكس عقارب الساعة بثلث دورة.
But now this has some reflectional symmetry.
أما بالنسبة لهذا فإن له تماثلات محورية.
I can reflect it in the line through X,
يمكن أن أعكسه بالنسبة للمحور المار بـ X،
or the line through Y,
أو بالنسبة للمحور المار بـ Y،
or the line through Z.
أو بالنسبة للمحور المار بـ Z.
Five symmetries and then of course the zeroth symmetry
خمس تماثلات و التماثل الصفر
where I just pick it up and leave it where it is.
حيث أرفعه و أضعه في مكانه.
So both of these objects have six symmetries.
وبذالك لهذين الشكلين ست تماثلات.
Now, I'm a great believer that mathematics is not a spectator sport,
أما الآن، إني أعتقد بشدة أن الرياضيات ليست رياضة للتفرج فقط،
and you have to do some mathematics
و يجب عليكم أن تمارسوا الرياضيات
in order to really understand it.
للتمكن من فهمها.
So here is a little question for you.
فهذا سؤال صغير لكم.
And I'm going to give a prize at the end of my talk
و في النهاية سأعطي جائزة
for the person who gets closest to the answer.
لمن سيكون الأقرب من الجواب.
The Rubik's Cube.
مكعب الروبيك.
How many symmetries does a Rubik's Cube have?
ما هو عدد التماثلات التي يمتلك مكعب الروبيك؟
How many things can I do to this object
كم مرة يمكن أن أحرك هذا الشكل
and put it down so it still looks like a cube?
ليبقى على شكل مكعب عندما أرجعه لمكانه؟
Okay? So I want you to think about that problem as we go on,
حسنا؟ أريدكم أن تفكروا في المسألة خلال ما يتبقى،
and count how many symmetries there are.
و أن تعدوا كم هنالك من تماثل.
And there will be a prize for the person who gets closest at the end.
وفي النهاية ستكون هنالك جائزة لأقرب جواب.
But let's go back down to symmetries that I got for these two objects.
لنعد إلى التماثلات التي يمتلكها هذين الشكلين.
What Galois realized: it isn't just the individual symmetries,
ما أدرك ڴالوا: ليس التماثلات وحدها،
but how they interact with each other
بل كيف تتفاعل بينها
which really characterizes the symmetry of an object.
و هو في الحقيقة ما يميز تماثل شكل ما.
If I do one magic trick move followed by another,
إذا طبقت خدعة الحركة مرة، و أتبعتها بأخرى،
the combination is a third magic trick move.
تعطي التركيبة خدعة حركة ثالثة.
And here we see Galois starting to develop
و هنا نشاهد ڴالوا بادئا بتطوير
a language to see the substance
لغة لمعاينة جوهر
of the things unseen, the sort of abstract idea
الأشياء الخفية، المفهوم التجريدي
of the symmetry underlying this physical object.
للتماثل الذي يوجد وراء الشكل المادي.
For example, what if I turn the starfish
على سبيل المثال، إذا أدرت نجم البحر
by a sixth of a turn,
بسدس دورة،
and then a third of a turn?
ثم بثلث دورة؟
So I've given names. The capital letters, A, B, C, D, E, F,
لقد إستعملت رموزا. الحروف الكبيرة، A ،B ،C ،D ،E ،F،
are the names for the rotations.
تشكل أسماء الحركات الدائرية.
B, for example, rotates the little yellow dot
B، على سبيل المثال، تدير النقطة الصفراء الصغيرة
to the B on the starfish. And so on.
إلى النقطة B على نجم البحر. نفس الشيء بالنسبة للآخرين.
So what if I do B, which is a sixth of a turn,
فماذا إذا قمت بـ B، و التي هي سدس دورة،
followed by C, which is a third of a turn?
متبوعة بـ C، ثلث دورة؟
Well let's do that. A sixth of a turn,
لنقم بهذا. سدس دورة،
followed by a third of a turn,
ثم ثلث دورة،
the combined effect is as if I had just rotated it by half a turn in one go.
تبدوا النتيجة كما أني أدرته بنصف دورة في مرة واحدة.
So the little table here records
يعبر هذا الجدول عن
how the algebra of these symmetries work.
الطريقة التي يعمل بها جبر هذه التماثلات.
I do one followed by another, the answer is
أقوم بحركة متبوعة بأخرى، الجواب هو
it's rotation D, half a turn.
الحركة D، نصف الدورة.
What I if I did it in the other order? Would it make any difference?
ماذا إذا غيرت الترتيب؟ هل سيغير شيئا؟
Let's see. Let's do the third of the turn first, and then the sixth of a turn.
فلنرى. لنقم بثلث الدورة أولا، ثم بسدس الدورة.
Of course, it doesn't make any difference.
طبعا، ليس هنالك أي فرق.
It still ends up at half a turn.
مازلنا نحصل على نصف دورة.
And there is some symmetry here in the way the symmetries interact with each other.
كما أن هنالك نوع من التماثل في الطريقة التي تتفاعل بها التماثلات.
But this is completely different to the symmetries of the triangle.
لكن هذا مختلف تماما عن تماثلات المثلث.
Let's see what happens if we do two symmetries
لنرى ماذا يحدث إذا طبقنا تماثلين
with the triangle, one after the other.
على المثلث، واحدا بعد الآخر.
Let's do a rotation by a third of a turn anticlockwise,
لنطبق ثلث دورة على عكس عقارب الساعة،
and reflect in the line through X.
و لنعكسه بالنسبة للمحور المار عبر X.
Well, the combined effect is as if I had just done the reflection in the line through Z
كنتيجة لهذا نحصل على الإنعكاس بالنسبة للمحور المار عبر Z
to start with.
كما لو طبقناه في البداية.
Now, let's do it in a different order.
و الآن، لنقم بعكس الترتيب.
Let's do the reflection in X first,
لنطبق الإنعكاس عبر X أولا،
followed by the rotation by a third of a turn anticlockwise.
متبوعا بثلث دورة على عكس عقارب الساعة.
The combined effect, the triangle ends up somewhere completely different.
نجد المثلث في تشكيلة مختلفة تماما.
It's as if it was reflected in the line through Y.
كما لو أنه قد عكس بالنسبة للمحور المار عبر Y.
Now it matters what order you do the operations in.
نجد في هذه المرة أن الترتيب مهم.
And this enables us to distinguish
يمكننا هذا من تمييز
why the symmetries of these objects --
لماذا تماثلات هذه الأشكال --
they both have six symmetries. So why shouldn't we say
يتوفر كلا الشكلين على ست تماثلات. فلماذا لا يجب
they have the same symmetries?
أن نقول بأن لهما نفس التماثلات؟
But the way the symmetries interact
لكن الطريقة التي تتفاعل بها التماثلات
enable us -- we've now got a language
تمكننا -- نملك الآن لغة
to distinguish why these symmetries are fundamentally different.
تمكننا من تحديد لماذا تختلف هذه التماثلات إختلافا جوهريا.
And you can try this when you go down to the pub, later on.
يمكنكم أن تجربوا هذا عندما تمرون من بعد بالحانة.
Take a beer mat and rotate it by a quarter of a turn,
خذوا شراب "بير ماط"، و أديروه ربع دورة،
then flip it. And then do it in the other order,
ثم أقلبوه. و افعلوا نفس الشيء في الترتيب الآخر،
and the picture will be facing in the opposite direction.
ستجدون أن الصورة توجد في الجهة المعاكسه.
Now, Galois produced some laws for how these tables -- how symmetries interact.
قد حدد ڴالوا بعض القوانين التي تحكم كيف أن هذه الجداول، كيف تتفاعل التماثلات.
It's almost like little Sudoku tables.
إنها تكاد تكون جداول سودوكو صغيرة.
You don't see any symmetry twice
لا تجدون مرتين أي تماثل
in any row or column.
في أي عمود أو صف.
And, using those rules, he was able to say
بواسطة هذه القوانين، تمكن من أن يؤكد
that there are in fact only two objects
بأن هنالك شكلين فقط
with six symmetries.
يحملان ست تماثلات.
And they'll be the same as the symmetries of the triangle,
و سيقوم بنفس الشيء بالنسبة لتماثلات المثلث،
or the symmetries of the six-pointed starfish.
أو تماثلات نجم البحر السداسي.
I think this is an amazing development.
إني أعتقد أن هذا يشكل تقدما مذهلا.
It's almost like the concept of number being developed for symmetry.
كأنما قمنا بتطوير مفهوم العدد من أجل التماثل.
In the front here, I've got one, two, three people
أمامي هنا، لدي واحد، إثنين، ثلاثة أشخاص
sitting on one, two, three chairs.
جالسين فوق واحد، إثنين، ثلاثة كراسي.
The people and the chairs are very different,
تختلف هؤلاء الأشخاص تماما،
but the number, the abstract idea of the number, is the same.
لكن العدد، فكرة العدد التجريدية، هي نفسها.
And we can see this now: we go back to the walls in the Alhambra.
يمكن لنا الآن أن نرى ذلك: لنعد إلى جدران قصر الحمراء.
Here are two very different walls,
لدينا هنا حائطان مختلفان،
very different geometric pictures.
صور هندسية جد مختلفة.
But, using the language of Galois,
لكن، عن طريق استخدام لغة ڴالوا،
we can understand that the underlying abstract symmetries of these things
نستطيع أن نفهم أن التماثلات التجريدية الكامنة وراء هذه الأشياء
are actually the same.
تتمثل في نفس الشيء.
For example, let's take this beautiful wall
لنأخذ على سبيل المثال هذا الجدار الجميل
with the triangles with a little twist on them.
الذي يحمل مثلثات محرفة قليلا.
You can rotate them by a sixth of a turn
يمكن أن نديرهم بسدس دورة
if you ignore the colors. We're not matching up the colors.
إذا تجاهلنا الألوان. إننا لا نقارن الألوان.
But the shapes match up if I rotate by a sixth of a turn
لكن تتطابق الأشكال إذا أدرتهم بسدس دورة
around the point where all the triangles meet.
حول النقطة حيث تتلاقى كل المثلثات.
What about the center of a triangle? I can rotate
و ماذا بالنسبة لمركز مثلث؟ يمكنني أن أديره
by a third of a turn around the center of the triangle,
بثلث دورة حول مركز المثلث،
and everything matches up.
و كل شيء يتطابق.
And then there is an interesting place halfway along an edge,
هنالك أيضا منطقة تثير الإهتمام في منتصف حرف،
where I can rotate by 180 degrees.
حيث يمكنني أن أدير ب ١٨٠ درجة.
And all the tiles match up again.
و لمرة أخرى تتطابق كل القطع.
So rotate along halfway along the edge, and they all match up.
و بذالك نجد أن كل شيء يتطابق بعد نصف دورة.
Now, let's move to the very different-looking wall in the Alhambra.
لنتنقل الآن إلى جدار آخر في قصر الحمراء.
And we find the same symmetries here, and the same interaction.
نجد هنا نفس التماثلات، و نفس التفاعلات.
So, there was a sixth of a turn. A third of a turn where the Z pieces meet.
فنجد هنا سدس دورة. ثلث دورة حيث تتلاقى القطع Z.
And the half a turn is halfway between the six pointed stars.
و نجد أيضا نصف دورة على نصف المسافة بين النجوم السداسية.
And although these walls look very different,
و على الرغم من أن هذه الجدران جد مختلفة،
Galois has produced a language to say
أنتج ڴالوا لغة لقول
that in fact the symmetries underlying these are exactly the same.
أن نفس التماثلات تكمن ورائها.
And it's a symmetry we call 6-3-2.
نسمي هذا التماثل ٦-٣-٢.
Here is another example in the Alhambra.
نجد هنا مثالا آخر في قصر الحمراء.
This is a wall, a ceiling, and a floor.
فهذا جدار، سقف، و أرضية.
They all look very different. But this language allows us to say
إنها تبدوا مختلفة جدا. لكن تمكننا هذه اللغة من القول
that they are representations of the same symmetrical abstract object,
بأنها تمثيلات لنفس التماثل التجريدي،
which we call 4-4-2. Nothing to do with football,
و الذي يسمى ٤-٤-٢. ليس له أي علاقة مع كرة القدم،
but because of the fact that there are two places where you can rotate
لكن لأن هنالك مكاننين حيث يمكن تدوير الشكل
by a quarter of a turn, and one by half a turn.
بربع دورة، و آخر بنصف دورة.
Now, this power of the language is even more,
تعطينا قوة هذه اللغة أكثر من هذا،
because Galois can say,
لأنها تمكن ڴالوا من قول،
"Did the Moorish artists discover all of the possible symmetries
"هل استكشف الفنانون البربر كل التماثلات الممكنة
on the walls in the Alhambra?"
على جدران قصر الحمراء؟"
And it turns out they almost did.
و لقد تبين أنهم اقتربوا من ذلك.
You can prove, using Galois' language,
يمكنكم تبيين ذالك، باستخدام لغة ڴالوا،
there are actually only 17
هنالك في حقيقة الأمر فقط ١٧
different symmetries that you can do in the walls in the Alhambra.
تماثل مختلف ممكن فوق جدران قصر الحمراء.
And they, if you try to produce a different wall with this 18th one,
و إذا حاولنا إنتاج التماثل رقم ١٨،
it will have to have the same symmetries as one of these 17.
فإنه سيكون مشابها لواحد من هؤلاء ١٧.
But these are things that we can see.
لكن هذه أشياء يمكننا أن نشاهدها.
And the power of Galois' mathematical language
و تكمن قوة لغة ڴالوا الرياضية
is it also allows us to create
في كون أنها تمكننا من إنتاج
symmetrical objects in the unseen world,
أشكال متماثلة في العالم التجريدي،
beyond the two-dimensional, three-dimensional,
بعيدا وراء البعدين، الثلاثة أبعاد،
all the way through to the four- or five- or infinite-dimensional space.
عبر الأربعة أو الخمسة أو الفضاء لا نهائي الأبعاد.
And that's where I work. I create
و هنالك حيث أشتغل. انا أنتج
mathematical objects, symmetrical objects,
أشكالا رياضية، أشكالا متماثلة،
using Galois' language,
عن طريق استخدام لغة ڴالوا،
in very high dimensional spaces.
في فضاءات ذات أبعاد جد كبيرة.
So I think it's a great example of things unseen,
إني أعتقد بذالك أن هذا مثال عظيم على الأشياء التجريدية،
which the power of mathematical language allows you to create.
التي يمكن إنتاجها بواسطة قوة اللغة الرياضية.
So, like Galois, I stayed up all last night
و بذالك، مثل ڴالوا، سهرت طوال الليلة الماضية
creating a new mathematical symmetrical object for you,
لأنتج لكم شكل رياضي متماثل جديد.
and I've got a picture of it here.
لدي هنا صورة له.
Well, unfortunately it isn't really a picture. If I could have my board
لكنها و للأسف ليست صورة تماما. إذا تمكنت من إحضار لوحتي
at the side here, great, excellent.
هنا في الجانب، عظيم، ممتاز.
Here we are. Unfortunately, I can't show you
حسنا. للأسف لا يمكنني أن أريكم
a picture of this symmetrical object.
صورة لهذا الشكل المتماثل.
But here is the language which describes
لكن لدي هنا اللغة التي تصف
how the symmetries interact.
كيف تتفاعل التماثلات.
Now, this new symmetrical object
لا يحمل هذا الشكل المتماثل الجديد
does not have a name yet.
أي إسم بعد.
Now, people like getting their names on things,
و يحب الناس استخدام أسمائهم لتسمية أشياء،
on craters on the moon
كالحفر فوق وجه القمر،
or new species of animals.
أو جنس جديد من الحيوانات.
So I'm going to give you the chance to get your name on a new symmetrical object
سأعطيكم الحظ لتعطوا إسمكم إلى شكل متماثل جديد
which hasn't been named before.
الذي لم يسمى من قبل.
And this thing -- species die away,
و هذا الشكل -- تموت الأجناس،
and moons kind of get hit by meteors and explode --
و ترتطم الأقمار بنيازك ثم تنفجر --
but this mathematical object will live forever.
لكن سيعيش هذا الشكل الرياضي أبدا.
It will make you immortal.
سيجعلكم خالدين.
In order to win this symmetrical object,
من أجل أن تفوزوا بهذا الشكل التماثلي،
what you have to do is to answer the question I asked you at the beginning.
يجب عليكم أن تجيبوا على السؤال الذي طرحته في البداية.
How many symmetries does a Rubik's Cube have?
ما هوعدد تماثلات مكعب الروبيكس؟
Okay, I'm going to sort you out.
حسنا، سأقوم بالفرز.
Rather than you all shouting out, I want you to count how many digits there are
بدلا من أن تصرخوا، أريدكم أن تعدوا كم هنالك من مرتبة في ارقامكم
in that number. Okay?
في ذالك العدد. حسنا؟
If you've got it as a factorial, you've got to expand the factorials.
إذا حصلتم على عدد عاملي، يجب عليكم أن تنشروا العاملي.
Okay, now if you want to play,
حسنا، و إذا أردتم اللعب الآن،
I want you to stand up, okay?
أريدكم أن تقفوا، حسنا؟
If you think you've got an estimate for how many digits,
إذا كنتم تظنون أن لديكم تقدير لعدد المراتب،
right -- we've already got one competitor here.
جيد -- لدينا متنافس هنا --
If you all stay down he wins it automatically.
أذا بقي جميعكم جالسين فسيفوز تلقائيا.
Okay. Excellent. So we've got four here, five, six.
حسنا. ممتاز. لدينا أربع هنا، خمس، ست.
Great. Excellent. That should get us going. All right.
عظيم. ممتاز. يمكننا الآن أن نواصل.
Anybody with five or less digits, you've got to sit down,
أي أحد لديه خمس مراتب أو أقل، يجب عليكم أن تجلسوا.
because you've underestimated.
و هذا لأن تقديركم كان بخسا.
Five or less digits. So, if you're in the tens of thousands you've got to sit down.
خمس مراتب أو أقل. فإذا كنتم في العشر آلاف فأجلسوا.
60 digits or more, you've got to sit down.
٦٠ مرتبة أو أكثر، فأجلسوا.
You've overestimated.
كان تقديركم مبالغا فيه.
20 digits or less, sit down.
٢٠ مرتبة أو أقل، أجلسوا.
How many digits are there in your number?
كم مرتبة يوجد في عددك؟
Two? So you should have sat down earlier.
إثنين؟ كان يجب عليك أن تجلس من قبل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Let's have the other ones, who sat down during the 20, up again. Okay?
لنرجع إلى الآخرين، الذين جلسوا في الـ ٢٠، قفوا مجددا. حسنا؟
If I told you 20 or less, stand up.
إذا قلت لكم ٢٠ أو أقل، قفوا.
Because this one. I think there were a few here.
لأن هذا. أظن أن بعضا منهم كانوا هنا.
The people who just last sat down.
آخر الأشخاص الذين جلسوا.
Okay, how many digits do you have in your number?
حسنا، كم رقما لديك في عددك؟
(Laughs)
(ضحك)
21. Okay good. How many do you have in yours?
٢١. حسنا جيد. كم لديك؟
18. So it goes to this lady here.
١٨. تمنح الجائزة للسيدة هنا.
21 is the closest.
٢١ هو الأقرب.
It actually has -- the number of symmetries in the Rubik's cube
هنالك في حقيقة الأمر -- يحمل عدد التماثلات في مكعب الروبيكس
has 25 digits.
عدد من ٢٥ رقم.
So now I need to name this object.
أريد الآن أن أسمي هذا الشكل.
So, what is your name?
فما هو إسمك؟
I need your surname. Symmetrical objects generally --
أحتاج إلى لقبك. تكون الأشكال المتماثلة في عامة الأمر --
spell it for me.
تهجي لي حروفه.
G-H-E-Z
ج-ه-أ-ز
No, SO2 has already been used, actually,
لا س.ؤ.٢ قد تم استخدامه من قبل، في حقيقة الأمر،
in the mathematical language. So you can't have that one.
في اللغة الرياضية. فلا يمكنك استعماله.
So Ghez, there we go. That's your new symmetrical object.
لدينا "جيز" إذا. هذا شكلك التماثلي الجديد.
You are now immortal.
فالآن أنتي خالدة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And if you'd like your own symmetrical object,
و إذا أردتم شكلكم المتماثل الشخصي،
I have a project raising money for a charity in Guatemala,
لدي مشروع، جمع المال من أجل دعم خيري في غواتيمالا،
where I will stay up all night and devise an object for you,
حيث سأسهر الليل كله لأصمم لكم الشكل،
for a donation to this charity to help kids get into education in Guatemala.
مقابل تبرع لإعانة الأطفال على الدخول إلى المدرسة، في غواتيمالا.
And I think what drives me, as a mathematician,
و إني أظن أن ما يدفعني لهذا، كعالم رياضيات،
are those things which are not seen, the things that we haven't discovered.
هو هذه الأشياء التي لا نرى، الأشياء التي لم نكتشف من بعد.
It's all the unanswered questions which make mathematics a living subject.
كل الأسئلة التي لم يجب عليها من بعد هي التي تجعل من الرياضيات موضوعا حيا.
And I will always come back to this quote from the Japanese "Essays in Idleness":
و سأقوم دوما بالرجوع إلى تلك المقولة اليابانية المقتطفة من "مقالات في الفراغ":
"In everything, uniformity is undesirable.
"في كل شيء، لا نحب النظام.
Leaving something incomplete makes it interesting,
جعل شيء ما غير كامل، يزيده أهمية،
and gives one the feeling that there is room for growth." Thank you.
و يعطينا إحساسا بأنه هنالك مجال للتحسين." شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)